(Music)
(موسيقى)
Good afternoon.
مساء الخير
As you're all aware, we face difficult economic times.
كما تعلمون جميعاً، نحن نواجه ظروفاً اقتصادية صعبة
I come to you with a modest proposal
وقد أتيت لكم باقتراح متواضع
for easing the financial burden.
لتخفيف الأعباء المالية.
This idea came to me while talking to
وقد خطرت لي هذه الفكرة خلال الحديث
a physicist friend of mine at MIT.
مع صديقٍ لي فيزيائي في معهد MIT
He was struggling to explain something to me:
والذي صعب عليه أن يشرح لي شيئاً:
a beautiful experiment that uses lasers to cool down matter.
تجربة جميلة استخدم بها الليزر لتهدئة الأجواء
Now he confused me from the very start,
وهو ما أصابني بالحيرة منذ البداية
because light doesn't cool things down.
لأن الضوء لا يعمل على تبريد الأشياء
It makes it hotter. It's happening right now.
بل يجعلها أسخن. مثل مايحصل الآن.
The reason that you can see me standing here is because
السبب الذي يجعلكم تروني واقفاً هنا هو
this room is filled with more than 100 quintillion photons,
لأن القاعة مليئة بأكثر من ١٠٠ كوينتليون فوتون
and they're moving randomly through the space, near the speed of light.
وهي تتحرك بشكل عشوائي في الفراغ، بمايقارب سرعة الضوء
All of them are different colors,
وجميعها بألوان مختلفة
they're rippling with different frequencies,
وتأتي موجاتها بترددات مختلفة
and they're bouncing off every surface, including me,
وترتد عن كل سطح بما في ذلك أنا
and some of those are flying directly into your eyes,
وبعضها تحلق مباشرة لعينيك
and that's why your brain is forming an image of me standing here.
وبذلك يكوّن دماغك صورة عني واقفاً هنا.
Now a laser is different.
والآن الليزر يختلف عن هذا
It also uses photons, but they're all synchronized,
يستخدم أيضاً الفوتونات لكن جميعها متزامنة
and if you focus them into a beam,
وإذا ركزتها معاً في شعاع
what you have is an incredibly useful tool.
ستحصل على أداة مفيدة بشكل لا يصدق
The control of a laser is so precise
التحكم في الليزر دقيق جداً
that you can perform surgery inside of an eye,
بالشكل الذي يمكنك من إجراء عملية داخل العين
you can use it to store massive amounts of data,
كما يمكنك استخدامك لتخزين كميات هائلة من البيانات
and you can use it for this beautiful experiment
ويمكنك استخدامه لهذه التجربة الجميلة
that my friend was struggling to explain.
التي حاول صديقي بصعوبة أن يشرحها.
First you trap atoms in a special bottle.
اولاً، عليك ان تحبس الذرات في زجاجه.
It uses electromagnetic fields to isolate the atoms
انها تستخدم حقول كهرومغناطسيه لفصل الذرات
from the noise of the environment.
من ضجيج البيئه
And the atoms themselves are quite violent,
والذرات بحد ذاتها عنيفه جدا
but if you fire lasers that are precisely tuned to the right frequency,
لكن اذا اطلقت اشعه ليزر وضبطها تحديداً للتردد الصحيح ،
an atom will briefly absorb those photons
الذره ستمتص هذه الفوتونات قليلاً
and tend to slow down.
وتميل لأن تتباطأ.
Little by little it gets colder
شيئاً فشيئاً تبرد
until eventually it approaches absolute zero.
الى ان تصل في النهايه الى درجه الصفر
Now if you use the right kind of atoms and you get them cold enough,
الان، اذا انت استخدمت النوع الصحيح من الذرات وجعلتها بارده كفايه،
something truly bizarre happens.
شيء غريب جداً سيحصل.
It's no longer a solid, a liquid or a gas.
انها لن تكون جماد، سائل، غاز بعد الان.
It enters a new state of matter called a superfluid.
انها تدخل حاله جديده تسمى السائل الهلامي
The atoms lose their individual identity,
الذرات تفقد هويتها الفرديه،
and the rules from the quantum world take over,
وقوانين عالم الفيزياء تأخذ محلها،
and that's what gives superfluids such spooky properties.
وهذا ما يعطي السوائل الهلاميه خصائصها الغريبه.
For example, if you shine light through a superfluid,
على سبيل المثال، اذا اشعلت ضوء خلال السائل الهلامي
it is able to slow photons down
فأنه لديه القدره على إبطاء الفوتونات
to 60 kilometers per hour.
الى ٦٠ كيلومتر في الساعه
Another spooky property is that it flows
خاصيه غريبه اخرى هي انه يطفو
with absolutely no viscosity or friction,
بلا لزوجه او احتكاك،
so if you were to take the lid off that bottle,
لذلك اذا كنت على وشك ان تفتح غطاء الزجاجه
it won't stay inside.
فانها لن تبقى بالداخل
A thin film will creep up the inside wall,
طبقه رقيقه ستزحف لأعلى الجدار،
flow over the top and right out the outside.
تطفو للاعلى الى الخارج .
Now of course, the moment that it does hit the outside environment,
الان طبعا، في اللحظه التي تصدم فيها بالبيئه الخارجيه،
and its temperature rises by even a fraction of a degree,
وترتفع حرارتها بجزء من الدرجه،
it immediately turns back into normal matter.
فأنها في الحال ترجع لحالتها الطبيعيه.
Superfluids are one of the most fragile things we've ever discovered.
السوئل الهلاميه واحده من اكثر الاشياء التي اكتشفناها هشاشه.
And this is the great pleasure of science:
وهنا تكمن المتعه الحقيقه في العلم:
the defeat of our intuition through experimentation.
هزيمه حدسنا من خلال التجارب العلميه.
But the experiment is not the end of the story,
لكن التجربة ليست نهايه القصه،
because you still have to transmit that knowledge to other people.
لان يبقى عليك ان تنقل تلك المعرفة الى اناس اخرين.
I have a Ph.D in molecular biology.
انا لدي دكتوراه في الاحياء الجزيئيه،
I still barely understand what most scientists are talking about.
وللان اجدني بالكاد افهم ما يقوله معظم العلماء
So as my friend was trying to explain that experiment,
اذا كما كان صديقي يحاول شرح تلك التجربة،
it seemed like the more he said,
بدا وكأنه كلما تكلم اكثر،
the less I understood.
كلما فهمت اقل،
Because if you're trying to give someone the big picture
بسبب انك كلما حاولت ان تشرح لاحدهم الصوره الكبيره
of a complex idea, to really capture its essence,
لفكرة معقده، ليفهم جوهرها الحقيقي،
the fewer words you use, the better.
كلما استخدمت كلمات اقل، كلما كان ذلك افضل.
In fact, the ideal may be to use no words at all.
في الحقيقه، المثالي هو عدم استخدام اي كلمات على الاطلاق.
I remember thinking, my friend could have explained
انا اتذكر اني فكرت، صديقي كان بإمكانه ان يشرح
that entire experiment with a dance.
التجربه بكاملها من خلال الرقص.
Of course, there never seem to be any dancers around when you need them.
بالطبع، يبدو انه لايوجد راقصين حولك عندما تحتاجهم.
Now, the idea is not as crazy as it sounds.
الان، الفكره ليست بالجنون كما تبدو
I started a contest four years ago called Dance Your Ph.D.
انا بدأت مسابقه قبل اربع سنوات تسمى ارقص رساله دكتوراتك.
Instead of explaining their research with words,
بدلا من ان يشرحوا ابحاثهم بالكلمات،
scientists have to explain it with dance.
العلماء يجب عليهم شرحها من خلال الرقص.
Now surprisingly, it seems to work.
الان بشكل مفاجىء، يبدو انها الفكره تعمل.
Dance really can make science easier to understand.
الرقص بإمكانه ان يجعل العلماء اسهل للفهم.
But don't take my word for it.
لكن لا تصدقوا كلماتي فقط
Go on the Internet and search for "Dance Your Ph.D."
اذهب الى الانترنت وابحث عن "Dance Your Ph.D."
There are hundreds of dancing scientists waiting for you.
هناك المئات من رقصات العلماء بإنتظارك.
The most surprising thing that I've learned while running this contest
اكثر شيء مفاجيء تعلمته خلال اداره تلك المسابقه
is that some scientists are now working directly with dancers on their research.
انه الان يوجد علماء يعملون مع الراقصين بشكل مباشر لشرح ابحاثهم.
For example, at the University of Minnesota,
على سبيل المثال، جامعه مينسوتا،
there's a biomedical engineer named David Odde,
هناك مهندس طبي حيوي يسمى ديفيد اود،
and he works with dancers to study how cells move.
وهو يعمل مع الراقصين لفهم كيف الخلايا تتحرك.
They do it by changing their shape.
يعملوها من خلال تغيير اشكالهم
When a chemical signal washes up on one side,
عندما تحمل اشاره كيميائيه على جهه واحده
it triggers the cell to expand its shape on that side,
فأنها تثير الخليه لتوسع من شكلها في تلك الجهه,
because the cell is constantly touching and tugging at the environment.
لان الخليه تلمس وتتجاذب بشكل مستمر في تلك البيئه.
So that allows cells to ooze along in the right directions.
وهذا يسمح للخليه بأن تنسل في ذلك الاتجاه
But what seems so slow and graceful from the outside
لكن ما يبدوا بطيء ورزين من الخارج
is really more like chaos inside,
انها اقرب للفوضى من الداخل،
because cells control their shape with a skeleton of rigid protein fibers,
لأن الخلايا تتحكم بشكلها من خلال هيكل من ألياف البروتين جامدة،
and those fibers are constantly falling apart.
وهذه الالياف تتهاوى بشكل مستمر.
But just as quickly as they explode,
لكن بنفس السرعه التي تنفجر فيها،
more proteins attach to the ends and grow them longer,
المزيد من البروتينات تتماسك عند النهايه وتزداد طولاً،
so it's constantly changing
لذا هي تتغير بأستمرار
just to remain exactly the same.
فقط لكي تبقى على نفس شكلها
Now, David builds mathematical models of this and then he tests those in the lab,
الان، ديفيد بنى نماذج رياضيه من هذه وبعد ذلك اختبرها في المعمل
but before he does that, he works with dancers
لكن قبل ذلك، هو عمل مع راقصين
to figure out what kinds of models to build in the first place.
ليعلم ماهي النماذج التي سوف يبنيها في المقام الاول.
It's basically efficient brainstorming,
انها بشكل اساسي وسيله عصف ذهني فعاله،
and when I visited David to learn about his research,
وعندما زرت ديفيد لأعلم عن ابحاثه،
he used dancers to explain it to me
هو استخدم الراقصين ليشرح لي
rather than the usual method: PowerPoint.
بدلا من الوسيله المعهوده: الباوربوينت.
And this brings me to my modest proposal.
وهذا يقودوني الى اقتراحي المتواضع.
I think that bad PowerPoint presentations
انا اعتقد ان عروض الباوربوينت السيئه
are a serious threat to the global economy.
هي تهديد جدي للأقتصاد العالمي.
(Laughter) (Applause)
(ضحك) (تصفيق)
Now it does depend on how you measure it, of course,
الان هو يعتمد على كيفيه حسابك له، بالطبع،
but one estimate has put the drain at 250 million dollars per day.
لكن أحد التقديرات قدرت استنزاف ٢٥٠ مليون دولار في اليوم الواحد.
Now that assumes half-hour presentations
الان لنقدر نصف ساعه لتقديم العروض
for an average audience of four people
لمتوسط عدد جمهور من اربعه اشخاص
with salaries of 35,000 dollars,
برواتب قدرها ٣٥٠٠٠ دولار
and it conservatively assumes that
سيقدر بتحفظ انه
about a quarter of the presentations are a complete waste of time,
ان ربع هذه العروض هي مضيعه للوقت،
and given that there are some apparently
وبعد حساب هذا هنالك كما يبدو
30 million PowerPoint presentations created every day,
٢٠ مليون عرض باوربوينت يصنع كل يوم
that would indeed add up to an annual waste
وهذا بالطبع سيضيف الى الهدر السنوي
of 100 billion dollars.
بمقدار ١٠٠ مليار دولار.
Of course, that's just the time we're losing
طبعاً، هذا فقط الوقت الذي نخسره
sitting through presentations.
بالجلوس خلال هذه العروض.
There are other costs, because PowerPoint is a tool,
هناك تكاليف اخرى ، بالطبع لان الباوربوينت مجرد وسيله،
and like any tool, it can and will be abused.
وكأي وسيله، بالأمكان اساءت استخدامها.
To borrow a concept from my country's CIA,
لأستعير مفهوم من وكالة الاستخبارات المركزية في بلدي.
it helps you to soften up your audience.
انها تساعدك لتلين جمهورك.
It distracts them with pretty pictures, irrelevant data.
انها تصرفهم بالصور الجميله، معلومات غير ذي صله.
It allows you to create the illusion of competence,
انها تسمح لك بخلق وهم بالجداره،
the illusion of simplicity,
وهم بالبساطه،
and most destructively, the illusion of understanding.
والاسوأ على الاطلاق، الوهم بالفهم
So now my country is 15 trillion dollars in debt.
والان بلدي في ديون بمقدار ١٥ ترليون دولار
Our leaders are working tirelessly to try and find ways to save money.
قادتنا يعملون بشكل مستمر لايجاد طرق لحفظ الاموال.
One idea is to drastically reduce public support for the arts.
وحده من الافكار هي بتقليل الدعم العام للفنون.
For example, our National Endowment for the Arts,
على سبيل المثال، صندوقنا الوطني للفنون،
with its $150 million budget,
بميزانيته ال ١٥٠ مليون،
slashing that program would immediately reduce the national debt
إلغاءه قد يخفض الدين الوطني على الفور
by about one one-thousandth of a percent.
بمقدار ١/١٠٠٠ في المائه.
One certainly can't argue with those numbers.
الشخص بالطبع لا يستطيع ان يجادل مع هذه الارقام
However, once we eliminate public funding for the arts,
بالمقابل، بمجرد ان نلغي الدعم العام للفنون
there will be some drawbacks.
سوف يكون هناك بعض السلبيات.
The artists on the street will swell the ranks of the unemployed.
الفنانين في الشارع سيضخم صفوف العاطلين عن العمل.
Many will turn to drug abuse and prostitution,
الكثير سيتجه للمخدرات او الدعاره،
and that will inevitably lower property values in urban neighborhoods.
التي من شأنها حتما خفض قيمة العقارات في الأحياء الحضرية.
All of this could wipe out the savings we're hoping to make in the first place.
كل هذا من الممكن ان يقضي على الادخار الذي نأمله في المقام الأول.
I shall now, therefore, humbly propose my own thoughts,
ولذلك، انا الان سأقدم بكل تواضع افكاري
which I hope will not be liable to the least objection.
التي اتمنى ان لا تكون عرضة لأي اعتراض.
Once we eliminate public funding for the artists,
بمجرد ان نلغي الدعم العام للفنانين،
let's put them back to work
دعونا نعينهم على رأس العمل مجدداً
by using them instead of PowerPoint.
بإستخدامهم بدلاً من عروض الباوربوينت.
As a test case, I propose we start with American dancers.
كحالة اختبار، أقترح أن نبدأ مع الراقصين الأمريكين.
After all, they are the most perishable of their kind,
في النهايه، هم الأكثر قابليه للفناء من نوعهم،
prone to injury and very slow to heal
عرضة للإصابة وبطيء في الشفاء
due to our health care system.
نتيجة لنظام الرعاية الصحية لدينا.
Rather than dancing our Ph.Ds,
بدلا من ان ترقص رسالتك في الدكتوراه،
we should use dance to explain all of our complex problems.
يجب ان نستخدم الرقص لنشرح افكارنا المعقده.
Imagine our politicians using dance
تخيل رجال السياسه لدينا يستخدموا الرقص
to explain why we must invade a foreign country
ليشرحوا لماذا يجب علينا ان نجتاح بلداً اجنبي
or bail out an investment bank.
او ان نكفل بنك استثمار.
It's sure to help.
انه بالتأكيد سيساعد.
Of course someday, in the deep future,
بالطبع يوماً ما، في المستقبل البعيد،
a technology of persuasion
تقنيه الاقناع
even more powerful than PowerPoint may be invented,
حتى اقوى من عروض الباوربوينت سوف تخترع،
rendering dancers unnecessary as tools of rhetoric.
مما سيجعل الراقصين غير ضروريين لها كأدوات للبلاغة.
However, I trust that by that day,
لكن، انا واثق انه حلول ذلك اليوم
we shall have passed this present financial calamity.
سنكون تخطينا كارثه الحاضر الماليه.
Perhaps by then we will be able to afford the luxury
ربما بحلول ذلك الوقت سوف تكون قادرة على تحمل الرفاهيه
of just sitting in an audience
او فقط الجلوس في جمهور
with no other purpose
بدون سبب اخر
than to witness the human form in motion.
سوى ان نشهد شكل الإنسان في الحركة.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)